Guide to the A.K. Best Collection 1983-2015
Montana State University-Bozeman Library
A.K. Best Collection
1983-2015
Montana State University-Bozeman Library, Merrill G Burlingame Special Collections P.O. Box 173320 Bozeman, MT 59717-3320 United States Phone (406) 994-4242 Fax (406) 994-2851 http://www.lib.montana.edu/archives/ University Archivist spcoll@www.lib.montana.edu
Collection 2603, MtBC, us
Best, A.K., 1933-
10.5 linear feet
The A.K. Best collection consists of letters, printed emails, drafts of various books, published articles, flies, and awards. Materials include business correspondence, manuscript material, published magazine articles and periodicals, photographs, and memorabilia ranging from 1983-2015.
Biographical Note
A.K. Best was born in 1933 in Iowa and currently resides in Colorado. Along with previously owning Front Range Anglers, Best is a prominent fly tier, angler, and angling author. Best published articles in magazines and journals such as Fly Rod and Reel, and Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, as well as writing several books including: A.K.’s Fly Box, Production Fly Tying, Fly Tying with A.K., Advanced Fly Tying, and Fly Fishing with A.K.
The A.K. Best collection consists of letters, printed emails, drafts of various books, published articles, flies, and awards. Materials include business correspondence, manuscript material, published magazine articles and periodicals, photographs, and memorabilia ranging from 1983-2015. Included is a copy of Production Fly Tying with handwritten notes from Best. An interview by Best detailing his life as an angler and a fly tier can be found in the Montana State University Angling Oral History Project.
Series 1 Correspondence
Series 2 Manuscript Material
Series 3 Published Material
Series 4 Photographs
Series 5 Memorabilia
Donor retains copyright to all printed materials.
Letters, printed emails, book drafts, articles, flies, and awards created or collected by A.K. Best were donated to Montana State University October 13, 2015.
Fishing and Canning; Literature; Sports and Recreation; Montana; Electroinc Records; Photographs
- Correspondence, Series 1
  This series includes business correspondence with Orvis. The documents include a project timeline, correspondence, invoices from Best, drawings of specialty tools A.K. curated, and a letter to McKenzie Fly Tackle Company addressing the unauthorized use of Best’s name on a product.
  - Orvis Business Correspondence (Box-folder 1/1)
- Manuscript Material, Series 2
  This series contains A.K. Best’s manuscript material for his books Advanced Fly Tying, A.K.’s Fly Box, Dying and Beaching Natural Fly Tying Materials 1st edition, Dyeing and Bleaching Natural Fly Tying Materials 2nd edition, Fly Fishing with A.K., Fly Tying with A.K., Production Fly Tying 1st edition, Production Fly Tying 2nd edition, and Solitary Trouting. Additional materials include an untitled poem, as well as early drafts for magazine articles for Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, Fly Rod and Reel, The Bamboo Fly Rod, Fly Tyer Magazine, Tightloop, and The Virtual Fly Fishing Shop. This series also contains various manuscripts from authors such as John Gierach, David Klausmeyer, Derrell Martin and Taylor Streit sent to Best for review. Magazine article drafts start in Box 10, folder 3, and manuscript material from other authors begin in Box 12. This series contains oversized materials that have been separated from the series, the separation is denoted by an asterisk (*) next to the folder from which the material was removed.
  - Advanced Fly Tying: Draft #3 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Advanced Fly Tying: Draft #4 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Advanced Fly Tying: Draft #5 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Advanced Fly Tying: Draft #6 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Advanced Fly Tying: Draft #7 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Advanced Fly Tying: Final Copy (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Advanced Fly Tying: Proof #1 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - Advanced Fly Tying: Draft with Correction (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Advanced Fly Tying: Miscellaneous Drafts (Box-folder 2/3-4)
  - Advanced Fly Tying: John Gierach Introduction (Box-folder 2/5)
  - Advanced Fly Tying: Correspondence and comments to publisher (Box-folder 2/6)
  - A.K.’s Fly Box: Draft #1 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - A.K.’s Fly Box: Draft #1 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - A.K.’s Fly Box: Draft #1 with Corrections (Box-folder 3/2-3)
  - A.K.’s Fly Box: Draft with Corrections (Box-folder 3/4-5)
  - A.K.’s Fly Box: Final Copy (Box-folder 3/6-7)
  - A.K.’s Fly Box: Dummy Copy * (Box-folder 3/8)
  - A.K.’s Fly Box: Correspondence with Publisher (Box-folder 3/9)
  - A.K.’s Fly Box: Floppy Discs (Box-folder 3/10)
  - A.K.’s Fly Box: Advance Copy with typo (Box-folder 3/11)
  - Dying and Bleaching Natural Fly Tying Materials: Draft #1 (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Dying and Bleaching Natural Fly Tying Materials: Final Copy (Box-folder 4/2)
  - Dying and Bleaching Natural Fly Tying Materials: Photographs (Box-folder 4/3)
  - Dying and Bleaching Natural Fly Tying Materials: Negatives (Box-folder 4/4)
  - Dying and Bleaching Natural Fly Tying Materials: Negative Proofs (Box-folder 4/5)
  - Dying and Bleaching Natural Fly Tying Materials: Slides (Box-folder 4/6)
  - Dyeing and Bleaching Natural Fly Tying Materials 2nd Edition: Draft #1 Author’s Copy (Box-folder 4/7)
  - Dyeing and Bleaching Natural Fly Tying Materials 2nd Edition: Draft #1 Editor’s Copy (Box-folder 4/8)
  - Dyeing and Bleaching Natural Fly Tying Materials 2nd Edition: Draft #4 (Box-folder 4/9)
  - Dyeing and Bleaching Natural Fly Tying Materials 2nd Edition: Manuscript Proof #1 Author’s Copy (Box-folder 4/10)
  - Dyeing and Bleaching Natural Fly Tying Materials 2nd Edition: Manuscript Proof #2 Author’s Copy (Box-folder 5/1)
  - Dyeing and Bleaching Natural Fly Tying Materials 2nd Edition: Manuscript Proof #2 (Box-folder 5/2)
  - Dyeing and Bleaching Natural Fly Tying Materials 2nd Edition: Manuscript Proof #3 (Box-folder 5/3)
  - Dyeing and Bleaching Natural Fly Tying Materials 2nd Edition: Dummy Copy * (Box-folder 5/4)
  - Dyeing and Bleaching Natural Fly Tying Materials 2nd Edition: Correspondence (Box-folder 5/5)
  - Fly Fishing with A.K.: Draft #5 (Box-folder 5/6)
  - Fly Fishing with A.K.: Draft Marked for Photographs (Box-folder 5/7)
  - Fly Fishing with A.K.: Partial Draft (Box-folder 5/8)
  - Fly Fishing with A.K.: Correspondence (Box-folder 5/9)
  - Fly Fishing with A.K.: Photograph Lists and Artwork (Box-folder 5/10)
  - Fly Tying with A.K.: Draft #1 (Box-folder 6/1)
    (partial)
  - Fly Tying with A.K.: Draft #3 (Box-folder 6/2)
  - Fly Tying with A.K.: Draft with Corrections (Box-folder 6/3)
  - Fly Tying with A.K.: Photograph List (Box-folder 6/4)
  - Fly Tying with A.K.: Correspondence (Box-folder 6/5)
  - Fly Tying with A.K.: DVDs with Photographs (Box-folder 6/6)
  - Fly Tying with A.K.: DVD Photograph Proof Sheet (Box-folder 6/7)
  - Production Fly Tying: Draft with Forward (Box-folder 6/8)
  - Production Fly Tying: Draft #1 (Box-folder 7/1-2)
  - Production Fly Tying: Early Draft (Box-folder 7/3)
  - Production Fly Tying: Index (Box-folder 7/4)
  - Production Fly Tying: Notes (Box-folder 7/5-6)
  - Production Fly Tying: Photographs (Box-folder 7/7)
  - Production Fly Tying: Photographs (Box-folder 8/1-2)
  - Production Fly Tying: Negatives (Box-folder 8/3)
  - Production Fly Tying: Negative Proof Sheet (Box-folder 8/4)
  - Production Fly Tying: Slides (Box-folder 8/5)
  - Production Fly Tying: Book with Notes (Box-folder 8/6)
  - Production Fly Tying 2nd Edition: Draft #1 (Box-folder 8/7)
  - Production Fly Tying 2nd Edition: Draft #3 (Box-folder 8/8-9)
  - Production Fly Tying 2nd Edition: Draft #4 (Box-folder 9/1)
  - Production Fly Tying 2nd Edition: Draft #5 (Box-folder 9/2)
  - Production Fly Tying 2nd Edition: Draft #6 (Box-folder 9/3)
  - Production Fly Tying 2nd Edition: Draft #7 (Box-folder 9/4)
  - Production Fly Tying 2nd Edition: Miscellaneous Draft Chapters (Box-folder 9/5)
  - Production Fly Tying 2nd Edition: Chapter #1 Proof (Box-folder 9/6)
  - Production Fly Tying 2nd Edition: Correspondence (Box-folder 9/7)
  - Production Fly Tying 2nd Edition: Floppy Discs (Box-folder 9/8)
  - Production Fly Tying 2nd Edition: Flies (Box-folder 9/9)
  - Solitary Trouting: Draft with Corrections (Box-folder 10/1)
  - Untiled Poem, 2001 (Box-folder 10/2)
  - The Bamboo Fly Rod: Drafts (Box-folder 10/3)
  - F.B.N.: Drafts, Correspondence, and Article Lists (Box-folder 10/4)
  - Fly Rod and Reel: Drafts (Box-folder 10/5-7)
  - Fly Rod and Reel Website: Article List, 2000 (Box-folder 10/8)
  - Fly Rod and Reel: Slides (Box-folder 10/9)
  - Fly Tyer Magazine: Drafts (Box-folder 10/10)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide: Drafts (Box-folder 11/1-6)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide: Article Lists, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 11/7)
  - TightLoop: Correspondence, Drafts, and Slides (Box-folder 11/8)
  - Virtual Fly Fishing Shop: Correspondence and Drafts (Box-folder 11/9)
  - David Klausmeyer: Tying Classic Fresh Water Streamers (Box-folder 11/1)
  - Derrell Martin: The Fly Fisher’s Craft * (Box-folder 12/2)
  - John Gierach: Dances with Trout Miscellaneous Drafts (Box-folder 12/3)
  - John Gierach: Sex, Death, and Fly Fishing Miscellaneous Drafts (Box-folder 12/4)
  - Taylor Streit: Instinctive Fly Fishing Proof (Box-folder 12/5)
- Published Material, Series 3
  This series contains published magazine articles and periodicals written by A.K. Best ranging from 1983-2015.This series also contains interviews of and published articles written about Best that include feature articles from John Gierach.
  - American Angler, 1991-2005 (Box-folder 13/1)
  - American Angler and Fly Tyer, 1988 (Box-folder 13/2)
  - American Fly Tyer, 1986 (Box-folder 13/3)
  - Angler Adventure News, 1995 (Box-folder 13/4)
  - An Auction to Benefit the North Atlantic Salmon Fund, 2003 (Box-folder 13/5)
  - The Bamboo Fly Rod, 1998 (Box-folder 13/6)
  - The Boulder Daily Camera, 1984-2010 (Box-folder 13/7)
  - Colorado Country Life, 2009 (Box-folder 13/8)
  - The Daily Times Call, 1987-1996 (Box-folder 13/9)
  - Field and Stream, 1990 (Box-folder 13/10)
  - Fishing Guide, 1995 (Box-folder 13/11)
  - Fishing World, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 13/12)
  - Flugfishe i Norden, 2006 (Box-folder 13/13)
  - The Fly Fisher, 1983 (Box-folder 13/14)
  - Fly Fisherman, 1988-1994 (Box-folder 13/15)
  - Fly Fisherman, 1995-2004 (Box-folder 14/1)
  - Fly Fisherman’s How to Catch Trout, 1988 (Box-folder 14/2)
  - Fly Fishing, 1984-1988 (Box-folder 14/3)
  - Fly Fishing News, 1990 (Box-folder 14/4)
  - Fly Fishing and Tying Journal, 2000-2002 (Box-folder 14/5)
  - Fly Fishing and Tying Journal, 2000-2006 (Box-folder 14/6)
  - Fly Rodders, 2005 (Box-folder 14/7)
  - Fly Rod and Reel, July 1989 - February 2001 (Box-folder 14/8)
  - Fly Rod and Reel, March 2001- March 2002 (Box-folder 14/9)
  - Fly Rod and Reel, April 2003-February 2004 (Box-folder 15/1)
  - Fly Rod and Reel, April 2003-February 2004 (Box-folder 15/2)
  - Fly Rod and Reel, March-December 2004 (Box-folder 15/3)
  - Fly Rod and Reel, January-June 2005 (Box-folder 15/4)
  - Fly Rod and Reel, July 2005-February 2009 (Box-folder 15/5)
  - Fly Rod and Reel, March-November 2009 (Box-folder 15/6)
  - Fly Rod and Reel, December 2009-Autumn 2010 (Box-folder 15/7)
  - Fly Rod and Reel, Spring 2011-Spring 2012 (Box-folder 16/1)
  - Fly Tackle Dealer, Spring 1988-April 1996 (Box-folder 16/2)
  - Fly Tyer, Summer 1995-Spring 1996 (Box-folder 16/3)
  - Fly Tyer, Summer 2004-Spring 2015 (Box-folder 16/4)
  - Gray’s Sporting Journal, February 1993-March 2005 (Box-folder 16/5)
  - Guide to Hunting and Fishing Outfitters, January 2005 (Box-folder 16/6)
  - High Country Sportsmen, September 1997 (Box-folder 16/7)
  - Hunter’s Angling Supplies, 1989 (Box-folder 16/8)
  - Hunting and Fishing Guide, January 2003 (Box-folder 16/9)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, April-December 1995 (Box-folder 17/1)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, February-December 1996 (Box-folder 17/2)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, February-October 1997 (Box-folder 17/3)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, February-July 1998 (Box-folder 17/4)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, August 1998-March 1999 (Box-folder 17/5)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, April-October 1999 (Box-folder 18/1)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, December 1999-July 2000 (Box-folder 18/2)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, August 2000-February 2001 (Box-folder 18/3)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, March-July 2001 (Box-folder 18/4)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, February-June 2002 (Box-folder 18/5)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, July-December 2002 (Box-folder 19/1)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, February-June 2003 (Box-folder 19/2)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, July-December 2003 (Box-folder 19/3)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, February-June 2004 (Box-folder 19/4)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, July-December 2004 (Box-folder 19/5)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, February-June 2005 (Box-folder 19/6)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, July 2005-February 2006 (Box-folder 20/1)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, March-August 2006 (Box-folder 20/2)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, September 2006-March 2007 (Box-folder 20/3)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, April-August 2007 (Box-folder 20/4)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, September 2007-April 2008 (Box-folder 20/5)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, May-October 2008 (Box-folder 20/6)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, December 2008-June 2009 (Box-folder 20/7)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, July 2009-February 2010 (Box-folder 21/1)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, March-August 2010 (Box-folder 21/2)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, September 2010-April 2011 (Box-folder 21/3)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, May-October 2011 (Box-folder 21/4)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, December 2011-July 2012 (Box-folder 21/5)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, August-December 2012 (Box-folder 21/6)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, February-September 2013 (Box-folder 21/7)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, October 2013-July 2014 (Box-folder 22/1)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, August 2014-March 2015 (Box-folder 22/2)
  - Mid Atlantic Fly Fishing Guide, April-December 2015 (Box-folder 22/3)
  - National Geographic, October 1993 (Box-folder 22/4)
  - Orvis News, March/April 2000 (Box-folder 22/5)
  - Outdoor Life, June 1996 (Box-folder 22/6)
  - Rocky Mountain News, 1988 (Box-folder 22/7)
  - Rocky Mountain Sportsmen, January-April 1987 (Box-folder 22/8)
  - Rod and Reel, January 1987-October 1988 (Box-folder 22/9)
  - Sports Afield, January 1987-July 1988 (Box-folder 22/10)
  - Sunday Times Call, 1987 (Box-folder 22/11)
  - Tightloop, Summer-Autumn 2001 (Box-folder 23/1)
  - Trout, Autumn 1988 (Box-folder 23/2)
  - Umpqua Flyer, Spring 1998 (Box-folder 23/3)
  - United Fly Tyers’ Roundtable (Box-folder 23/4)
  - Western Fly Tying, Summer 1996 (Box-folder 23/5)
  - Western Outdoors, April 1986 (Box-folder 23/6)
  - Unidentified Publications (Box-folder 23/7)
  - Ants (Box-folder 23/8)
  - Basic Dying (Box-folder 23/9)
  - Beetles (Box-folder 23/10)
  - Grasshopper (Box-folder 23/11)
  - Hackling Dry Flies (Box-folder 23/12)
  - Hair Wing Dry Flies (Box-folder 23/13)
  - Head Finishes (Box-folder 23/14)
  - Leader to Line Knot (Box-folder 23/15)
  - Soft Hackle Flies (Box-folder 23/16)
  - Tailing Mayflies (Box-folder 23/17)
  - Tying Thread (Box-folder 23/18)
  - Whip Finishing (Box-folder 23/19)
- Photographs, Series 4
  This series includes photographs of flies A.K. Best tied, as well as meadow streams, fish, portraits of Best, and 35mm slide transparencies meant for publication. This series contains oversized materials that have been separated from the series, the separation is denoted by an asterisk (*) next to the folder from which the material was removed.
  - 35mm Transparencies
  - #1-3 (Box-folder 23/20)
    - #1 Front Cover
    - #2 Chapter Pages
    - #3 A.K. Best
  - Photographs
  - Portraits, #4-7 (Box-folder 23/21)
    - #4 A.K. Best
    - #5 A.K. Best*
    - #6-7 A.K. Best with his class
  - Flies, #8-16 (Box-folder 23/22)
    - #8-9 Fly
    - #10 Flies on river
    - #11-16 Fly
  - Meadow Fishing, #17-26 (Box-folder 23/23)
    - #17 River
    - #18 Hooked Trout
    - #19-21 Trout in hand
    - #22-23 River
    - #24 Flies
    - #25-26 River
  - Meadow Fishing (Box-folder 23/24)
    [DVD]
- Memorabilia, Series 5
  This series includes flies tied by A.K. Best as well as memorabilia such as certificates awarded to Best over his lifetime and a hand drawn portrait of Best by Mike Gula. This series contains oversized materials that have been separated from the series, the separation is denoted by an asterisk (*) next to the folder from which the material was removed.
  - Memorabilia * (Box-folder 23/25)
  - Oral History Newspaper Clipping (Box-folder 23/26)
  - History of Fly Display Cases (Box-folder 24/1)
  - Flies (Box-folder 24/2-4)
  - Blue Wing Olive Cycle (Box-folder 25/1)
  - Dunes and Spinners (Box-folder 25/2)
  - Golden Fly (Box-folder 25/3)
  - Orvis Samples (Box-folder 25/4)
  - Hunter Samples (Box-folder 25/5)
  - Flies (Box-folder 25/6-7)
  - (Box Oversize*)
    The following oversized materials has been separated from Series 2, 4, and 5.
    - A.K.’s Fly Box: Dummy Copy
    - Dyeing and Bleaching Natural Fly Tying Materials 2nd Edition: Dummy Copy
    - Derrell Martin: The Fly Fisher’s Craft
    - Portrait of A.K. Best
    - Drawing of A.K. Best